<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Creating Controllers and Actions</title>

  <para>The Controller classes are stored in the folder <link
  linkend="???">EXT:sjr_offer/Classes/Controller/</link>. The name of the
  Controller is composed by the name of the Domain Model and the Suffix
  <classname>Controller</classname>. So the Controller
  <classname>Tx_SjrOffers_Controller_OfferController</classname> is assigned
  to the Aggegate Root Object
  <classname>Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer</classname>. And the Name of the
  Class file is <filename>OfferController.php</filename>.</para>

  <para>The Controller class must extend the class
  <classname>Tx_Extbase_MVC_Controller_ActionController</classname> which is
  part of Extbase. The individual Actions are combined in seperate methods.
  The method names have to end in <classname>Action</classname>. The body of
  <classname>OfferController</classname> thus looks like this:</para>

  <para><code>class Tx_SjrOffers_Controller_OfferController extends
  Tx_Extbase_MVC_Controller_ActionController {</code></para>

  <para><code>// Action methods will be following here</code></para>

  <para><code>}</code></para>

  <para>When realizing the desired tasks through <emphasis>Action</emphasis>
  methods you will often stumble upon very similar flows and patterns. Each
  task will be carried out by a single <emphasis>Action</emphasis> or a chain
  of <emphasis>Actions</emphasis>:</para>

  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>A list of Domain Objects is to be displayed.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A single Domain Object is to be displayed.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A new Domain Object is to be created.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>An existing Domain Object is to be edited.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>A Domain Object is to be deleted.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <para>We will shed some light on these recurring patterns in the following
  sections. Together with the schedule model you will learn the background to
  generate your own Flows.</para>

  <para><tip>
      <para>Note that you are free to choose the method names for your
      <emphasis>Actions</emphasis> as you like. Nevertheless we recommend to
      stick to the names presented here, to help other Developers to find
      their way through your Code.</para>
    </tip></para>

  <section version="5.0">
    <title>Flow Pattern "display a list of Domain Objects"</title>

    <para>The first pattern in our example fits the Action "<emphasis>display
    a list of all offers</emphasis>". One Action Method usually will be enough
    for implementing This. we choose <methodname>indexAction</methodname> as
    name of the Method:</para>

    <para><code>public function indexAction() { </code></para>

    <para><code>$offerRepository =
    t3lib_div_makeInstance('Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Repository_OfferRepository');
    </code></para>

    <para><code>$offers = $offerRepository-&gt;findAll(); </code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('offers', $offers); </code></para>

    <para><code>return $this-&gt;view-&gt;render(); </code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>This can be simplified even more. As described in chapter 4 in
    section "controlling the flow", it is not necessary to return the rendered
    content. Furthermore we avoid initializing the variable
    <methodname>$offers</methodname>, which we only use once. So we
    get:</para>

    <para><code>public function indexAction() { </code></para>

    <para><code>$offerRepository =
    t3lib_div_makeInstance('Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Repository_OfferRepository');
    </code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('offers',
    $offerRepository-&gt;findAll()); </code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>This Flow is prototypic for a task which merely has to give out
    data. Domain Objects are fetched from a Repository previously instatiated
    and passed to the View for future processing. Inside of our
    <classname>OfferController</classname> we have to make use of
    <classname>OfferRepository</classname> in the different Actions again and
    again. For that we don't have to intantiate the Repository in each and
    every Action, extbase offers the Method
    <classname>initializeAction()</classname>. It can be used for tasks
    concerning multiple Actions and is called before any Action is executed.
    In the class <classname>ActionController</classname> the body of this
    Method is empty. You can overwrite it in your own Controller though. In
    our case we assign the instance of our Repository to the Class Variable
    <classname>$offerRepository</classname>. Our Controller thus looks like
    this:</para>

    <para><code>protected $offerRepository;</code></para>

    <para><code></code></para>

    <para><code>pubilc function initializeActio() {</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;offerRepository =
    t3lib_div::makeInstance('Tx_JjrOffers_Domain_Repository_OfferRepository');</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><code></code></para>

    <para><code>public function indexAction() {</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('offers',
    $offerRepository-&gt;findAll()); </code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><classname>ActionController</classname> not only calls hte Method
    <classname>initializeAction()</classname>, which is executed before any
    Action in the Controller, but also a Method in the Form of
    <classname>initializeFooAction()</classname>, which is called only before
    the Method <classname>fooAction()</classname>. The Method for the
    initializing of Action is of course not only useful for preparing
    Repositories. You can also use them for integrating JavaScript libraries
    or to check if a specific FE user is logged in.</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>The trick of implementing an empty Method body in the super
        class, which is the "filled" in the subclass is called
        <emphasis>Template Pattern</emphasis>.</para>
      </tip></para>
  </section>

  <section version="5.0">
    <title>Flow Pattern "display a single Domain Object"</title>

    <para>The second pattern is best put into action by a single Mehod as
    well. We call it <classname>showAction()</classname>. In contrast to
    <classname>indexAction</classname> we have to to tell this Method from
    outside which Domain Object is to be displayed. In our case th offer to be
    shown is passed to the Method as Argument:</para>

    <para><code>/**</code></para>

    <para><code> * @param Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $offer The offer to
    be shown</code></para>

    <para><code> * @return string The rendered HTML string</code></para>

    <para><code> */</code></para>

    <para><code>public function showAction(Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer
    $offer) {</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('offer', $offer);</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>Ususally the display of a single Object is called by a link in
    Forntend. In our example extension it connects the list view by something
    like the following URL:</para>

    <para><code>http://localhost/index.php?id=123&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[offer]=3&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[action]=show&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[controller]=Offer</code></para>

    <para>Due to the 2 Arguments
    <code>tx_sjroffers_pi1[controller=Offer]</code> and
    <code>tx_sjroffers_pi1[action]=show</code>, the dispatcher of extbase
    passes the request to the <classname>OfferController</classname>. In the
    request we find the information that the Action <emphasis>show
    </emphasis>is to be called. Before passing on the further processing to
    the Method <classname>showAction()</classname>, the Controller tries to
    map the Arguments received by the URL on the arguments of the Method.
    Extbase maps the arguments by their names. In our example extbase detects
    the GET Argument <classname>tx_sjroffers_pi1[offer]=3
    </classname>corresponds to the Method Argument
    <classname>$offer</classname>:
    <classname>showAction(Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $offer)</classname>.
    The type of this Argument is fetched by extbase from the Method signature:
    <classname>showAction(Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $offer)</classname>.
    In case this so called <emphasis>Type Hint </emphasis>should not be
    present, or (e.g. for the types <emphasis>string </emphasis>or
    <emphasis>int</emphasis> in PHP) not possible, extbase reads the type from
    the commentary written above the Method: <classname>@param
    Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $offer</classname>.</para>

    <para>After successful assigning, the value of the incoming Argument has
    to be casted in the target type as well as checked for validity. (read
    more about validation in cahpter 9 in section "Validating Domain
    Objects"). In our case the incoming value is "3". Target type is the class
    <classname>Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer</classname>. So extbase
    interprets the the incoming value as uid of the Object to be created and
    sends a request to the <emphasis>Storage Backend</emphasis> to find an
    Object with this uid. If the Object can be reconstructed fully valid it is
    passed to the Method as argument. Inside of the Method
    <classname>showAction()</classname> the newly created Object is passed on
    to the view, which is taking care of the HTML output as usual.</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>Inside of the Template you can access all Properties of the
        Domain Object, including all existing child objects. Thus this Flow
        Pattern does not only cover single Domain Objects but in the event
        also a complex Aggregate.</para>
      </tip>If an Argument is identified as invalid, the already implemented
    Method <classname>errorAction()</classname> of
    <classname>ActionController</classname> is called instead of the Method
    <classname>showAction()</classname>. The Method then generates a message
    for the frontend user and passes the processing to the previous Action, in
    case it is given. The latter is especially useful with invalid form field
    input as you'll see in the following.</para>
  </section>

  <section version="5.0">
    <title>Flow Pattern "creating a new Domain Object"</title>

    <para>For the third Flow Pattern, the one fpor vreating a new Domain
    Object, two steps are required: First, a form for inputting the FDomain
    Data has to be shown in Frontend. Second, a new Domain Object hast to be
    created (using the incomin form data) and put in the appropriate
    Repository. We're going to implement these two steps in the Methods
    <classname>newAction() </classname>and
    <classname>createAction()</classname>.</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>We already described these steps in cahpter 3 in section
        "<remark>TODO: Insert correct section name</remark>." We shortly
        revise this Flow using our example extension and focus on some further
        aspects.</para>
      </tip>First the Method <classname>newAction() </classname>is called by a
    Link in frontend withe the following URL:</para>

    <para><code>http://localhost/index.php?id=123&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[oranization]=5&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[action]=new&amp;tx_sjroffers_pi1[controller]=Offer</code></para>

    <para>Extbase instantiates the <classname>Organization </classname>Object
    which is mapped to the Argument <classname>$organization, </classname>just
    as it was the case with the <classname>Offer </classname>Object in the
    Method <classname>showAction()</classname>. In the URL are no information
    (yet) though, which value the Argument <classname>$newOffer
    </classname>shall have. So the default value (=NULL) set in the Method
    signature is used. With these Arguments, the controller passes the further
    processing to the Method <classname>newAction()</classname>.</para>

    <para><code>/**</code></para>

    <para><code> * @param Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Organization $organization
    The organization</code></para>

    <para><code> * @param Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $offer The new offer
    object</code></para>

    <para><code> * @return string An HTML form for creating a new
    offer</code></para>

    <para><code> * @dontvalidate $newOffer</code></para>

    <para><code> */</code></para>

    <para><code>public function
    newAction(Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Organization $organization,
    Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer $newOffer = NULL) {</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('organization',$organization);</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('newOffer',$newOffer);</code></para>

    <para><code>$this-&gt;view-&gt;assign('regions',$this-&gt;regionRepository-&gt;findAll());</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>This Action passes to the view: in
    <classname>organization</classname> the <classname>organization
    </classname>Object, in <classname>newOffer</classname> NULL (to begin
    with) the and in <classname>region </classname>all <classname>region
    </classname>Objects contained in the
    <classname>RegionRepository</classname>. The view creates the output of
    the form in frontend, using a template, which we focus on in chapter 8 in
    section "<remark>TODO: Insert correct section name</remark>". After the
    user filled in the data of the offer and submitted the form, the Method
    <classname>createAction()</classname> is called. It expects as Arguments
    an <classname>Organization </classname>Object and an Object of the class
    <classname>Tx_SjrOffers_Domain_Model_Offer</classname>. For that extbase
    instantiates the Object and "fills" its Properties with the appropriate
    Form data. If all Arguments are valid, the Action
    <classname>createAction()</classname> is called.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>The new offer is allocated to the organization and inversly the
    organization is allocated to the offer. Thanks to this allocation extbase
    will cause the persistence of the new offer in the dispatcher before
    returning to TYPO3.</para>

    <para>After creating the new offer, the appropriate organization is to be
    displayed with all of its offers. We therefore start a new request
    (<emphasis>request-response-cycle</emphasis>) by redirecting to
    <classname>showAction()</classname> of the
    <classname>OrganizationController</classname> using the Method
    <classname>redirect()</classname>. The actual organization is hereby
    passed on as an argument. Inside the
    <classname>ActionCotroller</classname> you have the following Methods for
    redirecting to other Actions at your disposal:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>Using the <classname>redirect(</classname>) Method, you can start a
    new request-response-cycle on the spot, similar to clicking on a link: The
    given Action (specified in <classname>$actionName</classname>) of the
    appropriate controller (specified in
    <classname>$controllerName</classname>) in the given extension (specified
    in <classname>$extensionName</classname>) is called. If you did not
    specify a controller or extension, extbase assumes, that you stay in the
    same context. In the fourth parameter <classname>$arguments</classname>
    you can pass an Array of arguments. In our example<classname>
    array('organization' =&gt; $organization)</classname> <remark>TODO:
    "organization" should be "emphasis" in addition to "classname". I did not
    get it, sorry!</remark> would look like this in the URL:
    <classname>tx_sjroffers_pi1[organization]=5</classname>. The Array key is
    transcribed to the parameter name, while the organization object in
    <classname>$organization</classname> is transformed into the number 5,
    which is the appropriate UID. If you want to link to another page inside
    the TYPO3 installation, you can pass its uid in the 5th parameter
    (<classname>$pageUid</classname>). A delay before redirecting can be
    achieved by using the 6th parameter (<classname>$delay</classname>). By
    default the reason for redirecting is set to status code 303 (which means
    <emphasis>See Other</emphasis>).You can use the 7th parameter
    (<classname>$statusCode</classname>) to override this (for example with
    301, which means <emphasis>Moved Permanentely</emphasis>).</para>

    <para>In our example, the following code is sent to the Browser. It
    provokes the immedeate reload of the page with the given URL:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>The Method <classname>redirectToURI()</classname> corresponds to the
    Method <classname>redirect()</classname>, but you can directly set a URL
    respectively URI as string, e.g. <remark>TODO: insert Code</remark>. With
    this, you have all the freedom to do what you need. The Method
    <classname>forward()</classname>, at last, does a redirect of the request
    to another Action on the spot, just as the two redirect Methods. In
    contrast to them, no request-response-cycle ist started, though. The
    request Object is only updated with the details concerning Action,
    Controller and Extension, and then passed back to the dispatcher for
    processing. The dispatcher then passes on the actual
    <classname>Request-</classname> and
    <classname>Response-</classname>Objects to the appropriate Controller.
    Here, too, applies: If no Controller or Extension is set, the actual
    context is kept.</para>

    <para>This procedure can be done multiple times when calling a page. There
    is the risk, though, that the process runs into an infinite loop (A
    redirects to B, B redirects to A again). In this case, extbase stops the
    processing after some steps.</para>

    <para>There is another important difference to the redirect Methods. When
    redirecting using the Method <classname>forward()</classname>, new objects
    will not (yet) be persisted to database. This is not done until at the end
    of a request-response-cycle. Therefore no UID has yet been assigned to a
    new Object and the transcription to a URL parameter fails. You can
    manually trigger the action of presisting before the redirection, by using
    <classname>Tx_Extbase_Dispatcher::getPersistenceManager()-&gt;persistAll()</classname>,
    though.</para>

    <para>When calling the Method <classname>createAction(),</classname> we
    already described the case of all Arguments being valid. But what happens,
    if a Frontend user inserts invalid data or even manipulates the form to
    deliberately attack the website?<tip>
        <para>You find detailed information about validation and security in
        chapter 9</para>
      </tip></para>

    <para>Fluid adds multiple hidden fields to the form generated by the
    Method newAction(). These contain information about the origin of the form
    (__referrer) as well as, in encrypted form (__hmac), the structure of the
    form (shorted in the example below).</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>If now a validation error occurs when calling the Method
    createActio(), an error message ist saved and the processing is passed
    back to the previous Action, including all already inserted form data.
    Extbase reads the neccessary information from the hidden fields__referrer.
    In our case the Method newAction() is called again. In contrast to the
    first call, extbase now tries to create an (invalid) offer object from the
    form data and to pass it to the Method in $newOffer. Due to the annotation
    @dontvalidate $newOffer extbase this time acceptes the invalid object and
    displays the form once more.formerly filled in data is put in the fields
    again and the previously saved error message is displayed if the template
    is intenting so.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert OImage with caption: Fig. 7-1: Wrong input in
    the form of an offer leads to an error mesage (in this case a modal
    JavaScript window) </remark></para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>Standard error messages of extbase are not yet localized in
        Version 1.2. In section "Localize error messages" in chapter 8, we
        describe a possibility to translate the too, though.</para>
      </tip>Usig the hidden field __hmac, extbase compares in an early stage
    the structure of a form inbetween delivery to the browser and arrival of
    the form data. If the structure has changed, extbase assumes an evil
    assault and aborts the request with an error message. You can skip this
    check by annotting the Method with @dontverifyrequesthash, though. So you
    have two annotiations for Action Methods at your disposal:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>@dontvalidate $argumentName</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@dontverifyrequesthash</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>Using the annotation @dontvalidate $argumentName you tell
    extbase that the argument is not to be validated. If the argument is an
    Object, the validation of its properties is also bypassed.</para>

    <para>The annotation @dontverifyrequesthash makes extbase skip the check
    of integrity of the form. It is not checked any more, if the frontend user
    has e.g. added a password field. This annotation comes in handy for
    example, if you have to work with data of a form which you did not create
    yourself.</para>
  </section>

  <section version="5.0">
    <title>Flow Pattern "Editing an existing Domain Object"</title>

    <para>The flow pattern we will now present is quite similar to the
    previuos one. We again need two action Methods, which we call editAction()
    and updateAction() this time. The Method editsAction() provides the form
    for editing, while updateAction() updates the Object in the Repository. In
    contrast to newAction() it is not necessary to pass an organization to the
    Method editAction(). It is sufficvient to pass the offer to be edited as
    an Argument.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>Note once again the annotation @donvalidate $offer. The Method
    updateAction() receives the changed offer and updates it in the
    repository. Afterwards a new request os started and the organization is
    shown with its udated offers.</para>

    <para><warning>
        <para>Do not forget to expicitly update the cahnged Domain Object
        using update(). Extbase will not do tis automatically for you, for
        doing so could lead to unexpected results. For example if you have to
        manipulate the incomning Domain Object inside your Action
        Method.</para>
      </warning>At this point we have to ask ourselves how to prevent
    unauthorized changes of our Domain data. The organization and offer data
    are not to be changed by all visitors after all. So an administrator is
    allocated to each organization, authorized to cahnge the data of that
    organization. The administrator can change the contact data of the
    organization, create and delete offers and ocntact persons as well as edit
    existing offers. Securing against unauthorized acces can be done on
    different levels.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>On the level of TYPO3, access to the page and/or plugin is
          prohibited.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>inside the Action it is checked, if access is authorized. In
          our case it has to be checked if the administrator of the
          organization is logged in.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the template, links to Actions, to which the frontend user
          has no access are blinded out.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>Of these three levels, only the first two offer reliable
    protection. We do not take a closer look on the fiorst level in this book.
    You can find detailed information for setting up the rights framework in
    your TYPO3 system in the Core Documentation "Inside TYPO3" at
    http://typo3.org/documentation/document-library/core-documentation/doc_core_inside/4.2.0/view/2/4/.
    The second level, we are going to implement in all "critcal" Actions.
    Let's look at an example with the Method updateAction().</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>We ask a previously instantiated AccessControlService if the
    administrator of the organization reponsible for the offer is logged in in
    frontend. If yes, we do update the offer. If no, an error message is
    generated, which is displayed in the subsequently displayed organization
    overview.</para>

    <para>Extbase does not yet offer an API for access control. We therefore
    implemented an AccessControlService on ourselves. The description of the
    class is to be found in the file
    EXT:sjr_offers/Classes/Service/AccessControlService.php.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>The third level can easily be bypassed by manually typing the link
    or the form data. It therefore only reduces the confusion for honest
    visitors and the stimulus for the bad ones.Let's take a short look on this
    snippet from a template:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>A Service is often used to implement functionalitites that are
        need on mulitple places in your extensions and are not related to one
        Domain Object.</para>

        <para>Services are often stateless. In this context that means that
        their function does not dependend on previous access. This does not
        rule out dependency to the "environment". In our example you can be
        sure, that a verification by isLoggendIn() always leads to the same
        result, regardless of any earlier verification - given that the
        "environment" has not changed (considerably), e.g. by the
        Administrator logging out or even losing his acces rights.</para>

        <para>Service usually can be built as Singleton (implements
        t3lib_Singleton). You can find detailed information to Singleton in
        cahpter 2 in section "Singleton".</para>

        <para>The AccessControlService is not Part of the Domain of our
        extension. IT "belongs" to the Domain of the Content Management
        System. There are Domain Services also of course, like a Service
        creating a continuous invoice number. They are usually located in
        EXT:my_ext/Classes/Domain/Service/.</para>
      </tip></para>

    <para>We make use of an IfAuthenticatedViewHelper to acces the
    AccessControllService. The class file IfAuthenticatedViewHelper.php is in
    our case located in EXT:sjr_offers/Classes/ViewHelpers/Security/.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>The IfAuthenticatedViewHelper extends the If-ViewHelper of fluid and
    therefore provides the opportunity to use if-else branches. It delegates
    the access check to the AccessControlService. If the check gives a
    positive result, in our case a link with an edit icon is generated, which
    leads to the Method editAction of the OfferController.</para>
  </section>

  <section version="5.0">
    <title>Flow Pattern "Deleting a Domain Object"</title>

    <para>The last Flow pattern realizes the deleting of an existin Domain
    Object in a single Action. The appropriates Method DeleteAction() is kind
    of straightforward:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>The importat thing here is that you delete the given Offer from the
    Repository using the method remove(). After running through your
    extension, extbase will delete the assosciated record from the Database
    respectively mark it as deleted.</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>In principle it doesn't matter how you generate the result
        (usually HTML code) inside the Action. You can even decide to use the
        traditional way of building extensions - with SQL Queries ans
        maker-based Templating - inside yuor Action. We invite you to pursue
        the path we chose up to now, though.</para>
      </tip></para>

    <para>The Flow patterns we present here are meant to be blueprints for
    your own flows. In real life projects they may get way more complex. The
    Method indexAction() of the OfferController looks like this in it's final
    stage:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Insert Code</remark></para>

    <para>In the first few lines of the script, configuration options, set in
    the TypoScript template as comma seperated list, are transcribed to
    arrays. Then the information are passed to the view piece by piece.</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</section>
