<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Object-oriented programming in PHP</title>

  <para>Object-oriented programming is a Programming Paradigm, versatilely
  applied in extbase and the extensions built on it. In this section we will
  give an overview of the basic concepts of Object Orientation.</para>

  <para>Programs have a certain purpose, which is - generally speaking - to
  solve a problem. "Problem" does not necessarily mean error or defect but
  rather an actual task. This Problem usually has a concrete counterpart in
  real life.</para>

  <para>A Program could for example take care of the task of booking a cruise
  in the Indian Ocean. If so we obviously have a problem (a programmer that
  has been working to much and finally decided to go on vacation) and a
  program, promising recuperation by booking a coach on one of the luxury
  liners for him and his wife.</para>

  <para>Object Orientation assumes that a concrete problem is to be solved by
  a program, and a concrete problem is caused by real Objects. Therefore focus
  is on the Object. This can be abstract of course: it will not be something
  as concrete as a car or a ship all the time, but can also be a reservation,
  an accout or a graphical symbol.</para>

  <para>Objects are "containers" for data and corresponding functionality. The
  data of an object is stored in its <emphasis>Properties</emphasis>. The
  functionality is provided by <emphasis>Methods</emphasis>, which can for
  example alter the Properties of the Object. In regard to the cruise liner we
  can say, that it has a certain ammount of coaches, a length and width and a
  maximum speed. Further it has Methods to start the motor (and hopefully to
  stop it again also), change the direction as well as to increase thrust, for
  you can reach your holiday destination a bit faster.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Why Object Orientation after all?</title>

    <para>Surely some users will ask themselves why they should develop object
    orientated in the first place. Why not (just like until now) keep on
    developing procedural, thus stringing together functions. If we look at
    the roughly 4.300 extensions available for TYPO3 at the moment, we'll see
    that they are built with a class by default - but have been completed by
    the extension developer in a procedural way in about 95% of all cases.
    Procedural programming has some severe disadvantages though:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Properties and Methods belonging together with regard to content
        ca not be united. This methodology, called
        <emphasis>Encapsulation</emphasis> in Object Orientation, is
        necessary, if only because of clear arrangement.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>It is rather difficult to re-use code</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All Properties can be altered everywhere throughout the code.
        This leads to hard-to-find errors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Procedural code gets confusing easily. This is called Spaghetti
        code.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Furthermore Object Orientation mirrors the real world: Real Objects
    exist, and they all have properties and (most of them) methods. This fact
    is now represented in programming.</para>

    <para>In the following we'll talk about the object ship. We'll invoke this
    object, stock it with coaches, a motor and other useful stuff.
    Furthermore, there will be funtions, moving the ship, thus turning the
    motor on and off. Later we'll even create a luxury liner based on the
    general ship and equip it with a golf simulator and sattelite TV.</para>

    <para>On the following pages, we'll try to be as graphic as possible (but
    still semantically correct) to familiarize you with object orientation.
    There is a specific reason: The more you can identify with the Object and
    its Methods, the more open you'll be for the Theory behind Object
    Orientated Programming. Both is necessary for successfull programming –
    even though you'll often not be able to imagine the objects you'll later
    work with as clearly as in our examples.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Classes and Objects</title>

    <para>Let's now take a step back and imagine there'd be a blueprint for
    ships in general. We now focus not the ship but this blueprint. It is
    called <emphasis>Class</emphasis>, in this case is is the Class
    <classname>ship</classname>. In PHP this is written as follows;</para>

    <para><code>&lt;?php</code></para>

    <para><code>class ship {</code></para>

    <para><code>...</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><code>?&gt;</code></para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>In this piece of code we kept noting the necessary PHP tags at
        the beginning and end. We will spare them in the following examples to
        make the listings a bit shorter.</para>
      </tip>The key word <classname>class </classname>opens the Class and
    inside the curly brackets Properties and Methods are wirtten. we'll now
    add these Properties and Methods:</para>

    <para><code>class ship {</code></para>

    <para><code></code></para>

    <para><code>public $name;</code></para>

    <para><code>public $coaches;</code></para>

    <para><code>public $engineStatus;</code></para>

    <para><code>public $speed;</code></para>

    <para><code></code></para>

    <para><code>function startEngine() {}</code></para>

    <para><code>function stopEngine() {}</code></para>

    <para><code>function moveTo($location) {}</code></para>

    <para><code></code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>Our ship now has a name (<classname>$name</classname>), a number of
    coaches (<classname>$coaches</classname>) and a speed
    (<classname>$speed</classname>). In addition we built in a variable,
    containing the status of the engine
    (<classname>$engineStatus</classname>). A real ship, of course, has much
    more properties, all important somehow – for our our abstraction these few
    will be sufficient though. We'll focus on why every Property is marked
    with the key word <classname>public </classname>further down.</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>For Methods and Properties we use a notation called
        <emphasis>lowerCamelCase</emphasis>: The first letter is lower case
        and all other parts are added without blank or underscore in upper
        case. This is a convention used in extbase (as well as FLOW3).</para>
      </tip>We can also swith on the engine
    (<classname>startEngine()</classname>), travel with the ship to the
    desired destination (<classname>moveTo($location)</classname>) and switch
    off the engine again (<classname>stopEnginge()</classname>). Note that all
    Methods are empty, i.e. we have no content at all. We'll change this in
    the following examples, of course. The line containint Method name ad (if
    avallabe) parameters is called Method signature or method head. Everything
    contained by the Method ist called method body accordingly.</para>

    <para>Now we'll finally create an Object from our Class. The Class
    <classname>ship </classname>will be the blueprint and <classname>$fidelio
    </classname>the concrete Object.</para>

    <para><code>$fidelio = new Ship();</code></para>

    <para><code>// Display the Object</code></para>

    <para><code>var_dump($fidelio</code>);</para>

    <para>The key word new is used to create a concrete Objext from the Class.
    This Object is also called <emphasis>Instance </emphasis>and the creation
    process consequentially <emphasis>Instantiation</emphasis>. We can use the
    command <code>var_dump() </code>to closely examine the object. We'll see
    the following</para>

    <para><code>object(Ship)#1 (3) {</code></para>

    <para><code>["name"] =&gt; NUL </code></para>

    <para><code>["coaches"] =&gt; NULL</code></para>

    <para><code>["engineStatus"] =&gt; NULL</code></para>

    <para><code>["speed"] =&gt; NULL</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>We can clearly see that our Object has 4 Properties with a concrete
    value, at the moment still NULL, for we did not yet assign anything. We
    can instantiate as many Objects from a class as we like, and every single
    one will differ from the others – even if all of the Properties have the
    same values.</para>

    <para><code>$fidelio1 = new Ship();</code></para>

    <para><code>$fidelio2 = new Ship();</code></para>

    <para><code>if ($fidelio1 === $fidelio2) {</code></para>

    <para><code>echo 'Objects are identical!'</code></para>

    <para><code>} esle {</code></para>

    <para><code>echo 'Objects are not identical!'</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para>In this examle the output ist <code>Objects are not
    identical!</code></para>

    <section>
      <title>The arrow operator</title>

      <para>We are able to create an Object now, but of course it's Properties
      are still empty.We'll hurry to change this by assigning values to the
      Properties. For this, we use a special operator, the so called arrow
      operator (-&gt;). We can use it for getting access to the properties of
      an Object or calling Methods. In the following example, we set the name
      of the ship and call some Methods:</para>

      <para><code>$ship = new Ship();</code></para>

      <para><code>$ship-&gt;name = "FIDELIO";</code></para>

      <para><code>echo "The ship's Name is ". $ship-&gt;name;</code></para>

      <para><code>$ship-&gt;startEngine();</code></para>

      <para><code>$ship-&gt;moveTo('Bahamas');</code></para>

      <para><code>$ship-&gt;stopEngine();</code></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>$this</title>

      <para>Using the arrow operator we can now comfortably access Properties
      and Methods of an Object. But what to do, if we want to do this from
      inside a Method, e.g. to set <classname>$speed </classname>inside of the
      Method <classname>startEngine()</classname>? We don't know at this
      point, how an object to be instantiated later will be called. So we need
      a mechanism to do this indepentent from the name. This is done with the
      special variable <classname>$this</classname>.</para>

      <para><code>class Ship {</code></para>

      <para><code>...</code></para>

      <para><code>public $speed;</code></para>

      <para><code>...</code></para>

      <para><code>function startEngine() {</code></para>

      <para><code>$this-&gt;speed = 200;</code></para>

      <para><code>}</code></para>

      <para><code>}</code></para>

      <para>With <code>$this-&gt;speed </code>you can acces the Property
      "speed" in the acual Object, independently of it's name.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constructor</title>

      <para>It can be very useful to initialize an Object at the Moment of
      instantiating it. Surely there will be a certain number of coaches built
      in right away, when a new cruise liner is created - so that the future
      guest will not be forced to sleep in emergency accommodation. So we can
      define the number of coaches right when instantiating. The processing of
      the given value is done in a Method automatically called on creation of
      an Object, the so called <emphasis>Constructor</emphasis>. This special
      Method always has the name <classname>__construct() </classname>(the
      first two characters are underscores).</para>

      <para>The values received from instantiating are now passed on to the
      constructor as Argument and then assigned to the Properties
      <classname>§coaches </classname>respectively
      <classname>$name</classname>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Inheritance of Classes</title>

    <para>With the class we created we can already do a lot. We can create
    many ships and send them to the oceans of the world. But of course the
    shipping company always works on improving the offer of cruise liners.
    Increasingly big and beautiful ships are built. Also new offers for the
    passengers are added. FIDELIO2, for example, even has a little golf course
    based on deck.</para>

    <para>If we look behid the curtain of this new luxury liner though, we
    find that the shipping company only took a ship type FIDELIO and altered
    it a bit. The basis is the same. Therefore it makes no sense to completely
    redefine the new ship – instead we use the old definition and just add the
    golf course – just as the shipping company did. Technically speaking we
    extend an "old" Class definition by using the key word
    <code>extends</code>.</para>

    <para><code>class LuxuryLiner extends Ship {</code></para>

    <para><code>public $luxuryCoaches;</code></para>

    <para><code>function golfSimulatorStart() {</code></para>

    <para><code>echo 'Golf simulator on ship ' . $this-&gt;name . '
    started.';</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><code>function golfSimulatorStop() {</code></para>

    <para><code>echo 'Golf simulator on ship ' . $this-&gt;name . '
    stopped.';</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><code>}</code></para>

    <para><code>$luxuryShip = new LuxuryLiner('FIDELIO2','600')</code></para>

    <para>Our new luxury liner comes into existence as easy as that. We
    define, that the luxury liner just extends the Definition of the class
    <classname>Ship</classname>. The extended class (in or example
    <classname>Ship</classname>) is called <emphasis>parent class
    </emphasis>or <emphasis>superclass</emphasis>. The class formed by
    Extension (in our example <classname>LuxuryLiner</classname>) is called
    <emphasis>child class </emphasis>or <emphasis>sub class</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>The class <classname>LuxuryLiner</classname> now contains the
    complete configuration of the base class <classname>Ship</classname>
    (including all Properties and Methods) and defines additional Porperties
    (like the ammount of luxury coaches in
    <classname>$luxuryCoaches</classname>) and additional Methods (like
    <classname>golfSimulatorStart()</classname> and
    <classname>golfSimulatorStop()</classname>). Inside these Methods you can
    again access the Properties and Methods of the parent class by using
    <classname>$this</classname>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Overriding Properties and Methods</title>

      <para>Inside an inherited class you can not only access Properties and
      Methods of the parent class or define new ones. It's even possible to
      override the original Properties and Methods. This can be very useful,
      e.g. for giving a Method of a child class a new functionality. Let's
      have a look at the Method <classname>startEngine()</classname> for
      example:</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>Our luxury liner (of course) has an additional motor, so this has
      to be switched on also, if the Method
      <classname>startEngine()</classname> is called. The child class now
      overrides the Method of the parent class and so only the Method
      <classname>startEngine()</classname> of the child class is
      called.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access to the parent class through "parent"</title>

      <para>Overriding a Method comes in handy, but has a serious
      disadvantage. When changing the Method
      <classname>startEngine()</classname> in the parent class, we'd also have
      to change the Method in the child class. This is not only a source for
      errors but also kind of unconvenient. It would be better to just call
      the Method of the parent class and then add additional code before or
      after the call. That's exactly what can be done by using the key word
      <classname>parent</classname>. With
      <classname>parent::methodname()</classname> <remark>TODO: "methodname"
      should be "emphasis" in addition to "classname". I did not get it,
      sorry!</remark> the Method of the parent class can be accessed
      comfortably - so our former example can be re-written in a smarter
      way:</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Abstact classes</title>

      <para>Sometimes it is useful to define "placeholder Methods" in the
      parent class which are filled in the child class. These "placeholders"
      are called <emphasis>abstract Methods</emphasis>. A class containing
      abstract Methods is called <emphasis>abstract Class</emphasis>. For our
      ship there could be a Method <classname>setupCoaches()</classname>. Each
      type of ship is to be handled differently for each has a proper
      configuration. So each ship must have such a Method but the concrete
      implementation is to be done seperately for each ship type.</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>In the parent class we have defined only the body of the Method
      <classname>setupCoaches()</classname>. The key word
      <classname>abstract</classname> makes sure that the Method must be
      implemented in the child class. So using abstract classes, we can define
      which Methods have to be present later without having to implement them
      right away.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Interfaces</title>

      <para>Interfaces are a special case of abstract classes in which
      <emphasis>all Methods</emphasis> are abstract. Using Interfaces,
      specification and implementation of functionality can be kept apart. In
      our cruise example we have some ships supporting sattelite TV and some
      who don't. The ships who do, have the Methods
      <classname>enableTV()</classname> and
      <classname>disableTV()</classname>. It is useful to define an interface
      for that:</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>Using the key word <classname>implements</classname> it is made
      sure, that the class implements the given interface. All Methods in the
      interface definition then have to be realized. The object
      <classname>LuxuryLiner</classname> now is of the type
      <classname>Ship</classname> but also of the type
      <classname>SatteliteTV</classname>. It is also possible to implement not
      only one interface class but multiple, seperated by comma. Of course
      interfaces can also be inherited by other interfaces.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Visibilities: public, private and protected</title>

    <para>Access to Properties and Methods can be restricted by different
    visibilities to hide implementation details of a class. The meaning of a
    class can be communicated better like this, for implementation details in
    internal Methods can not be accessed from outside. The following
    visibilities exist:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>public</emphasis>: Properties and Methods with this
          visibility can be accessed from outside the Object. If no Visibility
          is defined, the behaviour of <classname>public</classname> is
          used.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>protected</emphasis>: Properties and Methods with
          visibility <classname>protected</classname> can only be accessed
          from inside the class and it's child classes.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>private</emphasis>: Properties and Methods set to
          <classname>private</classname> can only be accessed from inside the
          class itself, not from child classes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <section>
      <title>Access to Properties</title>

      <para>This small example demonstrates how to work with protected
      properties:</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>The <classname>LuxuryLiner</classname> may alter the property
      <classname>coaches</classname>, for this is
      <classname>protected</classname>. If it was
      <classname>private</classname> no access from inside of the child class
      would be possible. Access from outside of the hierarchy of inheritance
      (like in the last line of the example) is not possible. It would only be
      possible if the Property was <classname>public</classname>.</para>

      <para>We recommend to denfine all Properties as
      <classname>protected</classname>. Like that, they can not be altered any
      more from outside and you should use special Methods (called getter ans
      setter) to alter or read them. We'll explain the use of these Methods in
      the following section.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access to Methods</title>

      <para>All Methods the Object makes available to the outside have to be
      defined as <classname>public</classname>. All Methods containing
      implementation details, e.g. <classname>setupCoaches()</classname> in
      the above example, should be defined as
      <classname>protected</classname>. The visibility
      <classname>private</classname> should be used most rarely, for it
      prevents Methods from being overwritten or extended.</para>

      <para>Often you'll have to read or set Properties of an Object from
      outside. So you'll need special Methods that are able to set or get a
      property. These Methods are called <emphasis>setter</emphasis>
      respectively <emphasis>getter</emphasis>. See the example.</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>We now have a Method <classname>setCoaches()</classname> which
      sets the number of coaches. Furthermore it changes - depending on the
      number of coaches - the ship category. You now see the advantage: When
      using Methods to get and set the Properties, you can perform more
      complex operations, as e.g. setting of dependent Properties. This
      preserves consistency of the object. If you set
      <classname>$coaches</classname> and
      <classname>$classification</classname> to <classname>public</classname>,
      we could set the number of cabins to 1000 and classification to
      <classname>NORMAL</classname> - and our ship would end up being
      inconsistent.</para>

      <para><tip>
          <para>In extbase you'll find getter and setter Methods all over. No
          Property in extbase is set to <classname>public</classname>.</para>
        </tip></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Static Methods and Properties</title>

    <para>Until now we worked with Objects, instantiated from classes.
    Sometimes though, it does not make sense to generate a complete object,
    just to be able to use a function of a class. For this php offers the
    possibility to directly access Properties and Methods. These are then
    referred to as <classname>static Properties</classname> respectively
    <classname>static Methods</classname>. Take as a rule of thumb: static
    Properties are necessary, every time two instances of a class are to have
    a common Property. Static Methods are often used for function
    libraries.</para>

    <para>Transferred to our example this means, that all ships are
    constructed by the same shipyard. in case of technical emergency, all
    ships need to know the actual emergency phone number of this shipyard. So
    we save this number in a static Property
    <classname>$shipyardSupportTelephoneNumber</classname>:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

    <para>What happens here? We instantiate two different ships, which both
    have a problem and do contact the shipyard. Inside the method
    <classname>reportTechnicalProblem()</classname> you see that if you want
    to use static properties, you have to trigger them with the key word
    <classname>self::</classname>. If the emergency phone number now changes,
    the shipyard has to tell all the ships about the new number. For this ist
    uses the <emphasis>static method</emphasis>
    <classname>setShipyardSupportTelephoneNumber($newNumber)</classname>. For
    the Method is static, it is called through the scheme
    <classname>classname::methodname() <remark>TODO: "methodname" should be
    "emphasis" in addition to "classname". I did not get it,
    sorry!</remark><remark></remark></classname>, in our case
    <classname>LuxuryLiner::setShipyardSupportTelephoneNumber(...)</classname>.
    If you check the latter two problem reports, you see that all instances of
    the class use the new phone number. So both ship objects have acess to the
    same static variable
    <classname>$shipyardSupportTelephoneNumber</classname>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Important design- and architectural patterns</title>

    <para>In software engineering you'll sooner or later stumble upon design
    problems that are connatural and solved in a similar way. Clever people
    thought about <emphasis>design patterns</emphasis> aiming to be a general
    solution to a problem. Each design pattern is so to speak a solution
    template for a specific problem. We by now have multiple design patterns
    that are successfully approved in practice and therefore have found there
    way in modern programming and especially extbase. In the following we
    don't want to focus on concrete implementation of the design patterns, for
    this knowledge is not necessary for the usage of extbase. Nevertheless
    deeper knowledge in design patterns in general is indispensable for modern
    programming style, so it might be fruitful for you to learn about
    them</para>

    <para><tip>
        <para>Further information about design patterns can e.g. be found on
        <link linkend="???">http://sourcemaking.com/</link> or in the book
        <emphasis>PHP Design Patterns</emphasis> by Stephan Schmidt, published
        by O'Reilly.</para>
      </tip>From the big number of design patterns, we will have a closer look
    on two that are essential when programming with extbase:
    <emphasis>Singleton</emphasis> &amp;
    <emphasis>Prototype</emphasis>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Singleton</title>

      <para>This design pattern makes sure, that only one insatance of a class
      can exist <emphasis>at a time</emphasis>. In TYPO3 you can mark a class
      as singleton by letting it implement the interface
      <classname>t3lib_Singleton</classname>. An example: our luxury liners
      are all constructed in the same shipyard. So there is no sense in having
      more than one instance of the shipyard object:</para>

      <para><remark>TODO: Enter Code</remark></para>

      <para>In order to have the singletons correctly created you have to use
      the static TYPO3 Method
      <classname>t3lib_div::makeInstance()</classname>. This method gives back
      - as seen in the example above - always the same object, if you request
      a singleton.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Prototype</title>

      <para>Prototype is sort of the antagonist to Singleton. While for each
      class only one object is instantiated when using Singleton, it is
      explicitly allowed to have multiple instances when using Prototype. Each
      class not implementing the Interface
      <classname>t3lib_Singleton</classname> automatically is of the type
      <emphasis>Prototype</emphasis>.</para>

      <para><tip>
          <para>Originally for the design pattern
          <emphasis>Prototype</emphasis> is specified, that a new Object is to
          be created by cloning an Object prototype. We use Prototype as
          counterpart to Singleton, without a concrete pattern implementation
          in the background, though. For the functionality we experience, this
          does not make any difference: We invariably get back a new instance
          of a class.</para>
        </tip>Now that we refresehd your knowledge of object oriented
      programming, we can take a look at the deeper concepts of extbase:
      Domain Driven Design, Model View Controller and Test Driven Development.
      You'll spot the basics we just talked about in the following
      frequently.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
