<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>A journey through the Blog Example</title>

  <para>In this chapter we accompany you on a journey through a simple TYPO3
  extension. While traveling on this round trip you get to know more about the
  extension development with Extbase and Fluid and learn the most important
  stations and coordinates of the extension development with the help of a
  example extension. You first familiarize with the geography and the typical
  characteristics of a extension and find out, which processes run in the
  background. This knowledge will then help you in the creation of an own
  extension</para>

  <para>If you search for a specific manual for the creation of an extension,
  chapter 4 will show you the right set of tools. However we recommend you to
  build the fundamentals for that in this chapter. The journey that lies ahead
  of us, could also have the title "Europe in five days. If you discover nice
  places, you should visit them later without the travel group.</para>

  <para>It is a benefit, if you look into the original sourcecode while
  reading the text so the orientation in your own extension later will be much
  easier.</para>

  <note>
    <para>If you use a debugger, it can be interesting to follow a full cycle
    in the single step modus. For that you have to set a breakpoint in the
    file <filename>Dispatcher.php</filename>. You will find this class - like
    every other class of Extbase also - in the folder
    <filename>typo3/sysext/extbase/Classes/</filename>.</para>
  </note>

  <para>At the end of this chapter you will find a short comparison of the
  traditional way to code an extension and an approach with Extbase and
  Fluid.</para>

  <xi:include href="1-first-orientation.xml" />

  <xi:include href="2-the-stations-of-the-journey.xml" />

  <xi:include href="3-calling-the-extension.xml" />

  <xi:include href="4-and-action.xml" />

  <xi:include href="13-notes-for-migrating-users.xml" />
</chapter>
