<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Thanks</title>

  <section>
    <title>from Jochen and Sebastian</title>

    <para>Above all, we want to thank our families and partners for the
    understanding and the support, when we spent our afternoons and evenings
    with the book instead of them. Also our customers had to be patient the
    one or another time, when we developed Extbase or wrote the book, instead
    of continuing a customer project.</para>

    <para>TYPO3 would not exist without the dedication and vision of Kasper
    Skårhøy and without the tireless work of all community members, especially
    the TYPO3 core team. Here, we specifically want to thank the members who
    discovered and implemented many future-proof technologies for TYPO3 v5.
    Extbase would not be possible without this inspiration and
    guideline.</para>

    <para>Also when creating the book, we had generous support: A thank you
    goes to Patrick Lobacher, as he has written the section about Object
    Oriented Programming.</para>

    <para>Our special thanks goes to our editors, Alexandra Follenius and
    Inken Kiupel, who gave us a lot of feedback and comments to our texts, and
    thus had a great impact on the creating of this book. Also we want to
    thank the many unknown helping hands at O'Reilly, who ultimately created
    this book.</para>

    <para>Additionally, you are right now reading the English Version of this
    book, so we want to thank our translators for the dedication and work they
    have put into this project over the last months!</para>

    <para>Last but not least, we want to thank you: That you want to use
    Extbase and Fluid!</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>from the translators</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</section>
