<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<preface version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>TYPO3 is a powerful and mature content management system, which has a
  lot of features and a large degree of flexibility. However, the architecture
  of the currently used version 4 and the programming techniques which form
  the basis of it were the state of the art around the year 2000. That's why
  in the year 2006, after a thorough analysis of the current status, the
  decision was made to rewrite TYPO3 from scratch. A separation into a
  framework part and the real content management system TYPO3 seemed to make
  sense. Today, the framework FLOW3 is approaching production quality, and
  TYPO3 v5 is taking shape. The birth of Extbase and Fluid also took place in
  this phase of re-orientation.</para>

  <para>Extbase is a PHP based framework which supports developers in creating
  clean and easy-to-maintain TYPO3 extensions, which are also future proof, as
  the porting to TYPO3 v5 is eased a lot. The template engine Fluid makes sure
  that the user interface of the extension can easily be created
  individually.</para>

  <para>Extbase makes sure that there is a clear separation between different
  concerns, which make maintenance a lot more simple, because the code is
  structured modularily. Because of this modular design, the development time
  for initial development, but also for adjustments, drops, and thus also the
  costs associated with that. Extbase also lessens the burden of the developer
  when it comes to security-relevant and repeating tasks, for example the
  validation of arguments, the persistence of data, and the reading of
  TypoScript and FlexForm settings. Because of that, developers can focus on
  solving the problems of their clients.</para>

  <para>Because of the modern architeture and the usage of up-to-date software
  development paradigms, using Extbase needs different knowledge than before:
  Instead of "hacking together" an extension, programmers now must understand
  some concepts like Domain-Driven Design, and plan and model the extension
  more thoroughly before the implementation starts. In return, the source code
  of the extension becomes a lot better readable, more flexible and more
  extensible. Moreover, the used concepts are also applicable to other
  programming languages and frameworks, as the development paradigms like
  Domain-Driven Design or Model-View-Controller architecture can be used
  universally.</para>

  <para>Extensions which build on Extbase can be ported to TYPO3 v5 and FLOW3
  in a manageable fashion, as the structure of the extension, the naming
  conventions and the used APIs are almost the same. Hence, Extbase eases the
  transition to FLOW3 and TYPO3 v5 -- if you use Extbase, you can later easily
  switch to FLOW3 and TYPO3 v5.</para>

  <sidebar>
    <title>TYPO3 v4 and TYPO3 v5</title>

    <para>In the TYPO3 community, some products are developed in parallel
    right now. Here, they should be presented shortly. TYPO3 v4 is the
    established branch of TYPO3, which powers hundreds of thousands of
    installations world-wide. Right now, version 4.4 is the current version,
    and version 4.5 is in development.</para>

    <para>Because the internal structures of TYPO3 v4 were growing
    organically, and thus can be quite confusing, the TYPO3 team decided to
    begin a new development branch parallel to TYPO3 v4: TYPO3 v5 should be
    developed from scratch. While doing that, special attention has been on
    clean code and an easy and powerful infrastructure.<remark>The last
    sentence is strange -&gt; REWORK.</remark> It quickly emerged that we
    first needed to write a web application framework, before the CMS itself
    should be developed. This web application framework is FLOW3, and on that
    basis, TYPO3 v5 is now developed.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <para>We hope that Extbase and Fluid are the introduction to a completely
  new world of programming for you, such that you can now start learning the
  new concepts of FLOW3. At the beginning, you will learn a lot of new
  concepts, but over time, you will notice that Extbase and Fluid makes you a
  lot more productive than before. With a bit of luck, you might get into the
  "flow" which drove us while we developed Extbase and Fluid.</para>

  <para>Not only you as developer can profit from Extbase: Also the FLOW3
  development team can test many concepts for their real-world applicability,
  and remove bugs and inconsistencies, which occur in Extbase and
  Fluid.</para>

  <xi:include href="1-short-history.xml" />

  <xi:include href="2-target-audience.xml" />

  <xi:include href="3-structure.xml" />

  <xi:include href="4-typographic-conventions.xml" />

  <xi:include href="5-thanks.xml" />
</preface>
