<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Localizing and internationalizing an extension</title>

  <para>Particularly in business relationships there often is the need to
  provide a website in one or multiple languages. Therefore not only the
  translation of the website content has to be done but also the extensions
  which are used must be available in multiple languages. During extension
  development you should think about a possible translation later on and set
  the course according to this.</para>

  <para>The configuration options for localization inside TYPO3 are versatile.
  You will find a comprehensive description of all concepts and options in the
  <emphasis>Frontend Localization Guide
  (http://typo3.org/documentation/document-library/core-documentation/doc_l10nguide/current/)</emphasis>.
  For the following sections we assume a correct configuration of the
  localization, which is normally done in the TypoScript root template and
  looks like this:</para>

  <para><remark>TODO: insert code here</remark></para>

  <para>The selection of the frontend language is carried out with a parameter
  in the URL (<code>linkVars = L</code>). Important is the definition of the
  UID of the language (<code>sys_language_uid = 0</code>) and the language key
  of the language (<code>language = default</code>). When the URL of the
  website contains the parameter <code>L=1</code> the output occurs in german,
  if the parameter is not set the output of the website occurs in the default
  language (in our example in english).</para>

  <para>In the next section, we start with the translation of static text like
  captions of links which appear in templates. After this we go to translate
  the content of extensions, thus the domain objects. Finally we explain how
  you can adjust the date formats in accordance with the date conventions in
  the particular country.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Multi language Templates</title>

    <para>When you style the output of your extension using Fluid, you often
    have to localize particular terms or maybe short text in the templates. In
    the following sample template of the blog example which displays a single
    blog post with its comments there are some constant terms:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: insert code here</remark></para>

    <tip>
      <para>The template is a little bit simplified and reduced to the
      basic.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>First of all the text "By:" in front of the author of the post is
    hard coded in the template, as well as the caption "Comments". For the use
    of the extension on an English website this is no problem but if you want
    to use it on a German website, the texts "By" and "Comments" would be
    displayed instead of "Von" and "Kommentare". To make such text
    exchangeable it has to be removed from the template and inserted in a
    language file. Every text which is to be translated is given an identifier
    that can be inserted in the template later. Table 9-1 shows the identifier
    used in the sample and their translations into german and english.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Table 9-1: The texts how we want to translate
    them</emphasis></para>

    <para><table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Identifier</th>

            <th>English</th>

            <th>German</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>author_prefix</td>

            <td>By:</td>

            <td>Von:</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>comment_header</td>

            <td>Comments</td>

            <td>Kommentare</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table></para>

    <para>In TYPO3 (and also in Extbase) the language file, in which the
    translated terms are stored, is named <filename>locallang.xml</filename>.
    It should contain all terms that have to be translated, in our example
    "By:" and "Comments", and their translations. Using Extbase the the file
    <filename>locallang.xml</filename> must reside in the folder
    <filename>Resources/Private/Language/</filename>. To localize the above
    terms we create the <filename>locallang.xml </filename>file the following
    way:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: insert code here</remark></para>

    <para>The framework of the file includes the XML header, the root element
    of the XML file (<code>&lt;T3locallang&gt;</code>) and the description
    (<code>&lt;description&gt;</code>). The translations of the strings are in
    the <code>&lt;data type="array"&gt;</code> section. For every language
    there is a section <code>&lt;languageKey
    index="<emphasis>[language]</emphasis>" type="array"&gt;</code>. For every
    identifier is defined how it should be given out in a particular language
    in this section. In the above file the texts are stored in two languages:
    <emphasis>default</emphasis>, which equals to English and
    <emphasis>de</emphasis> for German.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>The TYPO3 Core API describes in detail the construction of the
      <filename>locallang.xml</filename> file
      (<emphasis>http://typo3.org/documentation/document-library/core-documentation/doc_core_api/4.2.0/view/7/2/</emphasis>).</para>
    </tip>

    <para>Now the placeholder for the translated terms must be inserted into
    the template. To do this, Fluid offers the ViewHelper
    <code>f:translate</code>. In this ViewHelper you give the identifier of
    the term to be inserted as argument <code>key</code> and the ViewHelper
    inserts either the german or the english translation according to the
    current language selection :</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;f:translate key="comment_header" /&gt;
&lt;!-- or --&gt;
{f:translate(key: 'comment_header')}</programlisting></para>

    <tip>
      <para>The used language is defined in the TypoScript template of the
      website. By default the english texts are used; but when with setting of
      the TypoScript setting <code>config.language = de</code> you can set the
      used language to german for example.</para>

      <para>To implement a language selection normally TypoScript conditions
      are used. These are comparable with an <code>if/else</code>
      block:</para>

      <para><programlisting>[globalVar = GP:L = 1]
  config.language = de
[else]
  config.language = default
[end]</programlisting></para>

      <para>When the URL of the website contains a parameter L=1, then the
      output is in German; if the parameter is not set the output is in the
      default language English.</para>

      <para>With the use of complex TypoScript conditions the language
      selection could be set to depend on the forwarded language of the
      browser.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>By replacing all terms of the template with the
    <code>translate</code> ViewHelper we could fit the output of the extension
    to the currently selected language. Here we have a look at the Fluid
    template for the output of the blog posts, now without the hardcoded
    english terms:</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: insert code here</remark></para>

    <tip>
      <para>Sometimes you have to localize a string in the PHP code, for
      example in the controller or inside of a ViewHelper. In that case you
      can use the static method
      <methodname>Tx_Extbase_Utility_Localization::translate($key,
      $extensionName)</methodname>. In addition to the key inside the
      locallang file also the name of the extension must be given as
      parameter, in order to load the correct locallang file.</para>
    </tip>

    <section>
      <title>Output localized strings using <code>sprintf</code></title>

      <para>In the above example we have outputted the name of the blog post
      author simply by using <code>{blog.author.fullName}</code>. Many
      languages have special rules on how names are to be used - especially in
      Thailand it is common to only show the first name and place the word
      "Khan" in front of it (which is a polite form). We want to enhance our
      template now as far as it can to output the name of the blog author
      according to the current language. In German and English this is the
      form "first name last name" and in Thai "Khan first name".</para>

      <para>Also for this use cases the <code>translate</code> ViewHelper can
      be used. With the aid of the array <code>arguments,</code> values can be
      embedded into the translated string. To do this, the syntax of the PHP
      function <code>sprintf</code> is used.</para>

      <para>If we want to implement the above example, we must assign the
      first name and the last name of the blog author separate to the
      <code>translate</code> ViewHelper:</para>

      <para><code>&lt;f:translate key="name" arguments="{1:
      post.author.firstName, 2: post.author.lastName}" /&gt;</code></para>

      <para>How should the corresponding string in the
      <filename>locallang.xml</filename> file looks like? It describes on
      which position the placeholder are to be inserted. For English and
      German it looks like this:</para>

      <para><code>&lt;label index="name"&gt;%1$s
      %2$s&lt;/label&gt;</code></para>

      <para>Important are the placeholder strings <code>%1$s</code> and
      <code>%2$s</code>. These will be replaced with the assigned parameters.
      Every placeholder starts with the % sign, followed by the position
      number inside the arguments array, starting with 1, followed by the $
      sign. After that the usual formatting specifications follows - in the
      example it is the data type <code>string (s)</code>. Now we can define
      for Thai, that "Khan" followed by the first name should be
      output:</para>

      <para><code>&lt;label index="name"&gt;Khan
      %1$s&lt;/label&gt;</code></para>

      <tip>
        <para>The keys in the arguments array of the ViewHelper have no
        relevance. We recommend to give them numbers like the positions
        (starting with 1), because it is easy understandable.</para>
      </tip>

      <tip>
        <para>For a full reference of the formatting options for
        <code>sprintf</code> you should have a look at the PHP documantation:
        <emphasis>http://php.net/manual/de/function.sprintf.php</emphasis>.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changing localized terms using TypoScript</title>

      <para>If you use an existing extension for a customer project, you
      sometimes find out that the extension is insufficient translated or that
      the translations have to be adjusted. TYPO3 offers the possibility to
      overwrite the localization of a term by TypoScript. Fluid also support
      this.</para>

      <para>If, for example, you want use the text "Remarks" instead of the
      text "Comments", you have to overwrite the identifier
      <code>comment_header </code>for the English language. For this you can
      add following line to your TypoScript template:</para>

      <para><code>plugin.tx_blogexample._LOCAL_LANG.default.comment_header =
      Remarks</code></para>

      <para>With this you will overwrite the localization of the term
      <code>comment_header</code> for the default language in the blog
      example. So you can adjust the translation of the texts like you wish,
      without changing the <filename>locallang.xml</filename> file.</para>

      <para>Until now we have shown how to translate static text of templates.
      Of course it is important that also the data of an extension is
      translated according to the national language. We will show this in the
      next section.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi language domain objects</title>

    <para>With TYPO3 you can localize the data sets in the backend. This also
    applies to domain data, because they are treated like "normal" data sets
    in the TYPO3 backend. To make your domain objects translateable you have
    to create additional fields in the database and tell TYPO3 about them. The
    class definitions must not be changed. Lets have a look at the required
    steps based on the <code>blog</code> class of the blog example. TYPO3
    needs 3 additional database fields which you should insert in the
    <filename>ext_tables.sql</filename> file:</para>

    <para><programlisting>CREATE TABLE tx_blogexample_domain_model_blog {
  ...
  sys_language_uid int(11) DEFAULT '0' NOT NULL,
  l18n_parent int(11) DEFAULT '0' NOT NULL,
  l18n_diffsource mediumblob NOT NULL,
  ...
};</programlisting></para>

    <para>You are free to choose the names of the database fields, but the
    names we use here are common in the world of TYPO3. In any case you have
    to tell TYPO3 which name you have chosen. This is done in the file
    <filename>ext_tables.php</filename> in the section <code>ctrl</code> of
    the corresponding database table.</para>

    <para><programlisting>$TCA['tx_blogexample_domain_model_blog'] = array (
  'ctrl' =&gt; array (
    ...
    'languageField' =&gt; 'sys_language_uid',
    'transOrigPointerField' =&gt; 'l18n_parent',
    'transOrigDiffSourceField' =&gt; 'l18n_diffsource',
    ...
  )
);</programlisting>The field <code>sys_language_uid</code> is used for storing
    the UID of the language in which the blog is written. Based on this UID
    Extbase choose the right translation dependending on the current
    TypoScript setting in <code>config.sys_language.uid</code>. In the field
    <code>l18n_parent</code> the UID of the original blog created in the
    default language, which the current blog is a translation of. The third
    field <code>l18n_diffsource</code> contains a snapshot of the source of
    the translation. This snapshot is used in the backend for creation of a
    differential view and is not used by Extbase.</para>

    <para>In the section <code>columns</code> of the <code>TCA</code> you have
    to configure the fields accordingly. The following configuration adds two
    fields to the backend form of the blog: one field for the editor to define
    the language of a data record and one field to select the data record the
    translation relates to.</para>

    <para><remark>TODO: insert code here</remark></para>

    <para>With it, the localization of the domain object is already
    configured. By adding <code>&amp;L=1</code> to the URL, the language of
    the frontend will be changed to german. If there is an existing
    translation of a blog, it will be shown. Otherwise the blog is output in
    the default language.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>You can control this behavior. If you set the option
      <code>config.sys_language_mode</code> to <code>strict</code> in the
      TypoScript configuration, then only these objects are shown which really
      have content in the frontend language. More information for this you
      will find in the <emphasis>Frontend Localization Guide</emphasis> of the
      <emphasis>Core Documentation</emphasis>.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>How TYPO3 v4 handles the localization of content offers two
    important specific features: The first is that all translations of a data
    record respectively a data record that is valid for all languages (UID of
    the language is 0 or -1) will be "added" to the data record in the default
    language. The second special feature is that always the UID of the record
    in the default language is bound for identification although the
    translated data record in the database table has anoher UID. This
    conception has a serious disadvantage: If you want to create a data record
    for a language that has no data record in the default language, you have
    to create the latter before. But with what content?</para>

    <tip>
      <para>In FLOW3 this is solved better. There only a "structure node"
      exists to which the content element is added with its different language
      parts. A default language in this spirit does not exist.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>Lets have an example for illustration: You create a blog in the
    default language English (=default). It is stored in the database like
    this:</para>

    <para><programlisting>uid:              7 (given by the database)
title:            "My first Blog"
sys_language_uid: 0 (selected in backend)
l18n_parent:      0 (no tranlation original exists)</programlisting></para>

    <para>After a while you create a German translation in the backend. In the
    database the following record is stored:</para>

    <para><programlisting>uid:              42 (given by the database)
title:            "Mein erster Blog"
sys_language_uid: 1 (selected in backend)
l18n_parent:      7 (selected in backend respectively given automaticly)</programlisting></para>

    <para>A link that references the single view of a blog looks like
    this:</para>

    <para><code>http://www.example.com/index.php?id=99&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[controller]=Blog&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[action]=show&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[blog]=7</code></para>

    <para>By adding <code>&amp;L=1</code> we referencing now the German
    version:</para>

    <para><code>http://www.example.com/index.php?id=99&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[controller]=Blog&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[action]=show&amp;tx_blogexample_pi1[blog]=7&amp;L=1</code></para>

    <para>Notice that the given UID in tx_blogexample_pi1[blog]=7 is not
    changed. There is not UID of the data record of the german translation
    (42). This has the advantage that only the parameter for the language
    selection is enough. Concurrently it has the disadvantage of a higher
    administration effort during persistance. Extbase will do this for you by
    carrying the UID of the language of the domain model and the UID of the
    data record in which the domain data is effectively stored as "hidden"
    properties of the <classname>AbstractDomainObject</classname> internally.
    In Table 9-2 you find for different actions in the frontend the behavior
    of Extbase for localized domain objects.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Table 9-2: Behavior of Extbase for localized domain
    objects in the frontend.</emphasis></para>

    <para><table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th />

            <th>no parameter L given, or L=0</th>

            <th>L=x (x&gt;0)</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>Display (index, list, show)</td>

            <td>Objects in the default language
            (<code>sys_language_uid=0</code>) respectively object for all
            languages (<code>sys_language_uid=-1</code>) are shown</td>

            <td>The objects are shown in the selected language x. If an object
            doesn't exist in the selected language the object of the default
            language is shown (except by
            <code>sys_language_mode=strict</code>)</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>Editing (edit, update)</td>

            <td>Like displaying an object. The domain data is stored in the
            "translated" data record, in the above example in the record with
            the UID 42.</td>

            <td>
              <remark>TODO: combine the columns 2 and 3</remark>
            </td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>Creation (new, create)</td>

            <td>Independent of the selected frontend language the domain
            object is first marked valid for all languages. The data is stored
            in a new record in whose field <code>sys_language_uid</code> the
            number -1 is inserted.</td>

            <td>
              <remark>TODO: combine the columns 2 and 3</remark>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table></para>

    <para>Extbase also supports all default functions of the localization of
    domain objects. It has its limits when a domain object should be created
    exclusively in a target language. Especially when no data record exists in
    the default language.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Localization of date output</title>

    <para>It often occurs that a date or time must be displayed in a template.
    Every language area has its own convention on how the date is to be
    displayed: While in Germany the date is displayed in the form
    <code>Day.Month.Year</code>, in the USA the form
    <code>Month/Day/Year</code> is used. Depending on the language the date
    must be formatted different.</para>

    <para>Generally the date or time is formatted by the
    <code>format.date</code> ViewHelper:</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;f:format.date date="{dateObject}" format="d.m.Y" /&gt;
&lt;!-- or --&gt;
{dateObject -&gt; f:format.date(format: 'd.m.Y')}</programlisting></para>

    <para>The date object <code>{dateObject}</code> is displayed with the date
    format given in the parameter <code>format</code>. This format string must
    be in a format which is readable by the PHP funtion <code>date()</code>
    and declares the format of the output. Table 9-3 shows the some important
    placeholders.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Table 9-3: Some place holder of date.</emphasis></para>

    <para><table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Format character</th>

            <th>Description</th>

            <th>Example</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>

        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>d</td>

            <td>Day of the month as number, double-digit, with leading
            zero</td>

            <td>01 ... 31</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>m</td>

            <td>Month as number, with leading zero</td>

            <td>01 ... 12</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>Y</td>

            <td>Year as number, with 4 digits</td>

            <td>2011</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>y</td>

            <td>Year as number, with 2 digits</td>

            <td>11</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>H</td>

            <td>Hour in 24 hour format</td>

            <td>00 ... 23</td>
          </tr>

          <tr>
            <td>i</td>

            <td>Minutes, with leading zero</td>

            <td>00 ... 59</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table></para>

    <para>But the ViewHelper has to be configured different. Depending on the
    language area, which is controlled by the language of the user, an other
    format string should be used. Here we combine the <code>format.date</code>
    ViewHelper with the <code>translate</code> ViewHelper which you got to
    know in the section "Multilanguage templates":</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;f:format.date date="{dateObject}" format="{f:translate(key: 'date_format')}" /&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>Than you can store an other format string for every language in the
    <filename>locallang.xml</filename> file and you can change the format
    string via TypoScript if needed. This method to translate content you got
    to know in the section "Multilanguage templates".</para>

    <tip>
      <para>There are other formatting ViewHelpers for adjusting the output of
      currencies or big numbers. These ViewHelpers all starts with
      <code>format</code>. You can find an overview of these ViewHelpers in
      Appendix C. These ViewHelpers can be used like the
      <code>f:format.date</code> ViewHelper you have just learned.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>In this section you have learned how you can translate and localize
    an extension. First we have worked on the localization of single terms in
    the template, after this we had a look at the content of the extension.
    Finally the customization of date information for country-specific formats
    where explained. In the next section you will see how constraints of the
    domain objects can be preserved.</para>
  </section>
</section>
