<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Configuring the Server</title>

  <para>Since TYPO3 is written in the PHP scrpting language, you will need a
  webserver like Apache with PHP (version 5.2 or 5.3) support, for your TYPO3
  development. Additionally TYPO3 requires a MySQL database for data storage.
  If you don't have a local development server yet, we recommend the XAMPP
  package (<emphasis>http://www.apachefriends.org/xampp.html</emphasis>). It
  will install Apache, PHP, MySQL and other useful tools on all established
  operating systems (Linux, Windows, Mac OS X). Now you can install TYPO3 on
  your test system.</para>

  <para>For production systems you are advised to use a PHP Opcode Cache like
  eAccelerator (<emphasis>http://eaccelerator.net</emphasis>), as it caches
  the compiled PHP code often reducing script loading times by more than half.
  By default eAccelerator will not cache PHP comments. However, as Extbase
  uses these comments to retrieve important information, eAccelerator must not
  omit them. To achieve this you need to configure eAccelerator with the
  option <code>--with-eaccelerator-doc-comment-inclusion</code>. A complete
  installation of eAccelerator will then work as follows: First download the
  eAccelerator source code and navigate to the source directory using the
  console. You have to adjust the eAccelerator source to your installed PHP
  version by running the command <code>phpize</code>. After this you can
  configure the eAccelerator source code not to remove the PHP comments by
  running <code>./configure --with-eaccelerator-doc-comment-inclusion</code>.
  Now compile eAccelerator with the command <code>make</code>. To finish the
  installation run <code>make install</code> as the <emphasis>root</emphasis>
  user.</para>

  <para>It might be neccessary to adjust your PHP configuration to load
  eAccelerator. Now you can check if your source code comments are preserved
  by using a TYPO3 instance. Install the <emphasis>extbase</emphasis>
  Extension in the TYPO3 backend by using the Extension Manager and then open
  the <emphasis>Reports</emphasis> module. Select the <emphasis>Status
  Report</emphasis> submodule and have a look at the
  <emphasis>extbase</emphasis> section, which will tell you whether the PHP
  comments are preserved or not.</para>

  <para><remark>TODO: Add picture 1-1</remark></para>
</section>
