<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mathml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
  <title>Configuring your IDE</title>

  <para>An Extension based on Extbase consists of many files, so it is helpful
  to use a PHP development environment (IDE) instead of a simple editor. Among
  syntax highlighting an IDE offers code completion in first place and a
  direct view of the code documentation. Some development environments also
  have an integrated debugger, which makes detecting errors easier and faster.
  To give you an example we'll show you how to set up NetBeans and Eclipse for
  Extension development. Both IDEs have comparable functionalities, so it
  depends on your personal preferences which one you should use.</para>

  <sidebar>
    <para>Sources</para>

    <para>The NetBeans IDE is offered for Windows, Linux and Mac OS X. We use
    NetBeans PHP, which you can download from
    <emphasis>http://netbeans.org</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Eclipse is also available for all important Operating Systems. The
    PHP IDE is called Eclipse PDT, which you can download from
    <emphasis>http://eclipse.org/pdt</emphasis>.</para>
  </sidebar>

  <para>In general you should create projects in NetBeans repectively (????)
  Eclipse for Extbase and Fluid. You will be able to have a look at the
  Extbase and Fluid source code and the documentation whenever you need
  it.</para>

  <para>Using NetBeans, in the <emphasis>File</emphasis> menu select
  <emphasis>New Project</emphasis> and choose <emphasis>PHP</emphasis> as
  category and then the entry <emphasis>PHP Application with Existing
  Sources</emphasis>. On the next page of the wizard you can select the
  Extension folder of Fluid or Extbase. If you use the development version of
  Extbase or Fluid you should select the directory
  <emphasis>/path-to-your-typo3-installation/typo3conf/ext/extbase/</emphasis>
  (or <emphasis>.../fluid/</emphasis>). If you want to use the version shipped
  with TYPO3, you'll find it at
  <emphasis>/path-to-your-typo3-installation/typo3/sysext/extbase/</emphasis>
  (or <emphasis>.../fluid/</emphasis>).</para>

  <tip>
    <para>By default NetBeans uses space chars for code indentation. But as
    the TYPO3 Coding Guidelines demand Tabs for indentation, you should
    configure NetBeans accordingly. Open the preferences dialogue of NetBeans
    and choose the entry <emphasis>Editor</emphasis>. Now, in the section
    <emphasis>Formatting</emphasis>, deactivate the option <emphasis>Expand
    Tabs to Spaces</emphasis> and adjust the options <emphasis>Number of
    Spaces per Indent</emphasis> and <emphasis>Tab Size</emphasis> to the same
    values (e.g. 4).</para>
  </tip>

  <para>In Eclipse creating projects for Extbase and Fluid will work like
  this: Click on <emphasis>File</emphasis> → <emphasis>New Project</emphasis>
  and choose <emphasis>Create project from existing source</emphasis>. Then
  choose the according folder for Extbase or Fluid and provide a name for the
  project. Click on <emphasis>Finish</emphasis> to create the project with
  your settings.</para>

  <para>When developing an Extension by yourself you should also create a
  dedicated project for it in NetBeans or Eclipse.</para>
</section>
